Guide to the Hugh Nissenson Papers, 1942-2013 SPEC.RARE.0138
Ohio State University Libraries Special Collections
Hugh Nissenson Papers
1942-2013
SPEC.RARE.0138
Ohio State University Libraries Special Collections
29.78 Cubic feet
Hugh Nissenson was an American author whose fiction dealt extensively with American life, depression, and Judaism. The Hugh Nissenson Papers date from the 1940s to 2013, and contain drafts and manuscripts of published and unpublished materials, an extensive autobiographical journal detailing his writing process, and other papers relating to Nissenson's personal and professional life.
(56) 5" letter document boxes; (2) 5" legal boxes; (1) 2.5" legal documet box; (1) flat box; (4) costume boxes; (3) oversize document boxes; (1) oversize folder
Nissenson, Hugh
Arrangement of Materials
This collection is arranged in 4 series: Series 1: Professional Papers Series 2: Published Works Series 3: Personal Papers Series 4: Unpublished Works
Acquisitions Information
Donated by Marilyn Nissenson, 2014 August
Access to Materials
Materials in this collection are available for patron research, but may be used in the Thompson Library Special Collections reading room only.
Biographical Note
Hugh Nissenson (1933-2013) was an American author. Nissenson was born in New York City and lived there his whole life. He was educated at the Fieldstone School in the Bronx and received an undergraduate degree from Swarthmore College in 1955. Nissenson's published works include non-fiction and autobiographical work, but he was most well-known for his fiction, including his short-stories and novels. Nissenson published one memoir, three collections of short stories and five novels, in addition to numerous short stories published in serials and periodicals. Nissenson's work dealt with issues of life in America and also touched extensively on Judaism, a topic explored in his first novel "My Own Ground." While critically well received, his works were never commercially successful, an issue which contributed to his ongoing depression.
Scope and Contents
The Hugh Nissenson Papers contain materials dated between the 1940s and 2013. Included in the collection are drafts and manuscripts of published and unpublished materials, an extensive autobiographical journal detailing his writing process, and other papers relating to Nissenson's personal and professional life. These materials primarily take the form of loose-leaf, letter size paper, or bound volumes such as datebooks or journals.
Nissenson, Hugh; Authors, American--New York (State)--New York--20th century; Autobiographies (documents); Depression in men--Fiction; Diaries; Judaism
- Professional Papers, 1966-2007; Series 1
  Scope and Contents
  The Professional Papers series contains papers directly related to Nissenon's career as a professional writer without being one of his creative works. This includes awards, interviews, speeches he gave, reviews of other writer's work, and commentary about his own work by other writers. This series spans the 1960s to the 2000s.
  - Awards, 1966-2002; Subseries 1.1
    This sub-series contains two awards bestowed upon Nissenson for his works "A Pile of Stones" (awarded in 1966) and "The Song of the Earth" (awarded in 2002). These awards take the form of paper documents.
    - Edward Lewis Wallant Memorial Book Award, 1966 (Box 58, Folder 2)
    - Gaylacic Spectrum Award, 2002 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Biography, 1970s, 2003; Subseries 1.2
    Contains publisher-requested biographies for inclusion in press and marketing materials. These biographical documents were written by Nissenson himself.
    - Biography, 2003 (Box 19, Folder 6)
    - Biography, circa 1970s (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Interviews, 2003, undated; Subseries 1.3
    This sub-series contains two interviews with Nissenson, the undated Vialione interview being done for an Italian publication. The Klin interview took place in 2003.
    - Fabiana Vialione, undated (Box 19, Folder 11)
    - Richard Klin, 2003 (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - Commentary, 1979-2003; Subseries 1.4
    This sub-series contains copies of articles written about Nissenson's work by other individuals not in the form of a review, generally by academics. These range in date from 1979 to the 2000s, with one document undated.
    - History and Myth in the Novel, 1979 (Box 58, Folder 3)
    - Commentary, Birns, circa 2003 (Box 19, Folder 8)
    - "Spare, Original, and Strange", undated (Box 19, Folder 9)
    - VOICES - Hugh Nissenson, 2000s (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - Reviews, 1969, undated; Subseries 1.5
    This sub-series contains reviews Nissenson did of other published materials, in 1969 and another written at an unknown time.
    - Reviews, 1969 (Box 19, Folder 13)
    - Miss Rhode Island, undated (Box 19, Folder 14)
  - Speeches, 1975-2007, undated; Subseries 1.6
    This sub-series contains speeches that Nissenson gave in his capacity as a professional writer. These spanned his life from the 1970s to the 2000s and in many cases were undated, and even untitled, providing little context to the circumstances when they were given.
    - Amos Speech, undated (Box 19, Folder 15)
    - The Beast Within, 2007 (Box 19, Folder 16)
    - Claudia Ortese Memorial Lecture, Undated (Box 19, Folder 17)
    - Claudia Ortese Memorial Lecture, Undated (Box 19, Folder 18)
    - Cleveland Speech, Undated (Box 19, Folder 19)
    - Fieldstone Speech, Undated (Box 19, Folder 20)
    - Fitzgerald and the Future, Undated (Box 19, Folder 21)
    - Lectures at Manhatlanville, 1975 (Box 19, Folder 22)
    - Lecture at Westchester, 1975 (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - Literary Creativity and the Publishing Industry, Undated (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - Present Tense 10th Celebration, 1983 (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - Song of Earth Lecture, Undated (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - Speech for YMHA, Undated (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - Yale Lecture Notes, Undated (Box 20, Folder 6)
    - Untitled, 1994 (Box 20, Folder 7)
    - Untitled, Undated (Box 20, Folder 8)
    - Untitled, Undated (Box 20, Folder 9)
    - Untitled, Undated (Box 20, Folder 10)
    - Untitled, Undated (Box 20, Folder 11)
    - Untitled, Undated (Box 20, Folder 12)
    - Untitled, Undated (Box 20, Folder 13)
- Published Works, 1960-2007; Series 2
  The Published Works series contains materials present in looseleaf, letter sized paper, generally not bound in any way. Papers present either represent non-fiction, such as his reporting on the war crimes trials of Eichmann and Barbie, and also his autobiographical work, or American fiction, as in the case of all his short stories and novels. Materials were produced from 1960 to 2011.
  - Eichmann Traial, Application Approval, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Eichmann Trial, Notes, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - The Law, manuscript, circa 1960 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - The Law, manuscript, circa 1960 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - The Law, clipping, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - The Well, clipping, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - The Groom on Zlota Street, clipping, circa 1960s (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - The Groom on Zlota Street, manuscript, circa 1960s (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - The American, clipping, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - The American, manuscript, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - The American, draft, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - The American, draft, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - The Throne of Good, drafts/notes (1 of 2), 1964 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - The Throne of Good, drafts/notes (2 of 2), 1964 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - The Throne of Good, notes, 1964 (Box 57, Folder 5)
  - The Throne of Good, manuscript, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Masada, script, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Notes From the Frontier, "Economy", circa 1967 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Notes From the Frontier, "The Children", circa 1967 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Notes From the Frontier, "People - Characters", circa 1967 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Notes From the Frontier, "Religion", circa 1967 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Notes From the Frontier, "Archaeology", circa 1967 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Notes From the Frontier, "The Place", circa 1967 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Notes From the Frontier, "Emigrants, Kiryat Shmone", circa 1967 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Notes From the Frontier, review blurbs, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Notes From the Frontier, draft, circa 1967 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Notes From the Frontier, draft, circa 1967 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Notes From the Frontier, Book Proposal, circa 1967 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Notes From the Frontier, manuscript, circa 1968 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Notes From the Frontier, manuscript, circa 1968 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Notes From the Frontier, manuscript, circa 1968 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Notes From the Frontier, book proposal, circa 1968 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Notes From the Frontier, manuscript (1 of 2), circa 1968 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Notes From the Frontier, manuscript (2 of 2), circa 1968 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - The Crazy Old Man, draft, circa 1968 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - An Event of the Night, drafts, circa 1969 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - The Remnant Part II, final script, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - The Remnant, working script, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - The Remnant, bridge materials, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - The Remnant, bridge scenes, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Charity, manuscript, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Charity, manuscript, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Going Up, drafts, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Grace, drafts, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Grace, research, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Lamentations, drafts/manuscript, 1970 (Box 57, Folder 3)
  - In the Reign of Peace, first proof, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - In the Reign of Peace, first proof, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - In the Reign of Peace, first proof, 1971 (Box 57, Folder 1)
  - In the Reign of Peace, first proof, 1971 (Box 57, Folder 2)
  - On Jaffa Rd, notes/drafts, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - My Own Ground, notes, 1960s (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - My Own Ground, early draft, 1960s (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - My Own Ground, notebook, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - My Own Ground, notebook, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - My Own Ground, grant application, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - My Own Ground, manuscript, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - My Own Ground, chapter 10, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - My Own Groud, draft, 1970s (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - My Own Ground, draft, 1970s (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - My Own Ground, draft, 1970s (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - My Own Ground, chapter 2, 1970s (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - My Own Ground, draft, 1970s (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - My Own Ground, revisions, 1970s (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - My Own Ground, revisions, 1970s (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - My Own Ground, draft, 1970s (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - My Own Ground, draft, circa 1970s (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - My Own Ground, early draft, circa 1970s (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - My Own Ground, draft (1 of 2), 1970s (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - My Own Ground, draft (2 of 2), 1970s (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - My Own Ground, draft, circa 1970s (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - My Own Ground, draft, circa 1970s (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - My Own Ground, draft, 1970s (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - My Own Ground, early draft, circa 1970s (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - My Own Ground, draft, circa 1970s (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - My Own Ground, draft, circa 1970s (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - My Own Ground, book jacket, circa 1976 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - My Own Ground, photocopy, circa 1976 (Box 57, Folder 4)
  - My Own Ground, manuscript pages, circa 1970s (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Under Siege, draft, circa 1974 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Under Siege, incomplete manuscript, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Eight Stories, draft, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Eight Stories, photocopy, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Eight Stories, photocopies, circa 1976 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Eight Stories, introduction and notes, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Hope, draft, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Hope, drafts, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - The Tree of Life, research, 1966 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - The Tree of Life, early draft, circa 1970s (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - The Tree of Life, letters from grade schoolers, 1978 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - The Tree of Life, grant application, 1978 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - The Tree of Life, notes/drafts, 1979 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - The Tree of Life, notes, 1980-1981 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - The Tree of Life, notes, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - The Tree of Life, draft, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - The Tree of Life, reviews, 1985 (Box 57, Folder 6)
  - The Tree of Life, book information sheet, circa 1985 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - The Tree of Life, author questionaire, circa 1985 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - The Tree of Life, printers copy (1 of 3), circa 1985 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - The Tree of Life, printers copy (2 of 3), circa 1985 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - The Tree of Life, printers copy (3 of 3), circa 1985 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - The Tree of Life, draft (1 of 2), circa 1985 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - The Tree of Life, draft (2 of 2), circa 1985 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - The Tree of Life, printers copy, circa 1985 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - The Tree of Life, signature, circa 1985 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - The Tree of Life, master copy (1 of 2), circa 1985 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - The Tree of Life, manuscript, circa 1985 (Box 57, Folder 7)
  - The Tree of Life, master copy (2 of 2), circa 1985 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - The Tree of Life, research, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - The Tree of Life, draft, circa 1980s (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - The Tree of Life, draft, 1980s (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - The Tree of Life, draft with notes, 1980s (Box 57, Folder 8)
  - The Tree of Life, concluding letter, 1999 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - The Tree of Life, bookmark, 2000 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - The Tree of Life, notes/drafts, undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - The Tree of Life, research, undated (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - The Tree of Life, notes, undated (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - The Tree of Life, manuscript (1 of 2), undated (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - The Tree of Life, manuscript (2 of 2), undated (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - The Tree of Life, manuscript (1 of 2), undated (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - The Tree of Life, manuscript (2 of 2), undated (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - The Tree of Life, manuscript (1 of 2), undated (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - The Tree of Life, manuscript (2 of 2), undated (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - The Tree of Life, notebook, undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - The Tree of Life, maps, undated (Box 63, Folder 16)
  - The Tree of Life, slides, undated (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - The Tree of Life, research, undated (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - The Tree of Life, manuscript, undated (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Barbie Trial, clippings/press materials, 1987 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - The Elephant and My Jewish Problem, catalog copy, 1988 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - The Elephant and My Jewish Problem, manuscript, undated (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - The Elephant and My Jewish Problem, draft, undated (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - The Song of the Earth, poetry, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - The Song of the Earth, notes/draft, 1992 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - The Song of the Earth, draft, 1996 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - The Song of the Earth, manuscript (1 of 2), 1998 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - The Song of the Earth, manuscript (2 of 2), 1998 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - The Song of the Earth, images, 1999 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - The Song of the Earth, "First Final Copy, 10/1/99" (1 of 2), 1999 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - The Song of the Earth, "First Final Copy, 10/1/99" (2 of 2), 1999 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - The Song of the Earth, calendars, circa 1990s (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - The Song of the Earth, page, 1990s (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - The Song of the Earth, draft, 1990s (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - The Song of the Earth, draft, 1990s (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - The Song of the Earth, draft, 1990s (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - The Song of the Earth, manuscript (1 of 3), 1990s (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - The Song of the Earth, manuscript (2 of 3), 1990s (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - The Song of the Earth, manuscript (3 of 3), 1990s (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - The Song of the Earth, research/notes, 1990s (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - The Song of the Earth, timeline, 1990s (Box 60, Folder 1)
  - The Song of the Earth, illustrated pages, 2000 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - The Song of the Earth, manuscript, 2000 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - The Song of the Earth, reviews, 2000-2001 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - The Song of the Earth, reviews, 2001 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - The Song of the Earth, reviews, 2001 (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - The Song of the Earth, seminar papers, 2001 (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - The Song of the Earth, book jacket, circa 2001 (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - The Song of the Earth, setting manuscript (1 of 2), 2001 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - The Song of the Earth, setting manuscript (2 of 2), 2001 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - A Sense of the Past, drafts, 2000 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - The Days of Awe, images, 2001 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - The Days of Awe, research, 2001 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - The Days of Awe, research, 2002 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - The Days of Awe, research, 2002 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - The Days of Awe, calendar, 2002 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - The Days of Awe, research, 2002 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - The Days of Awe, research, 2002 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - The Days of Awe, research, 2002 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - The Days of Awe, research, 2003 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - The Days of Awe, research, 2003 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - The Days of Awe, research, 2003 (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - The Days of Awe, Odin images, 2003 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - The Days of Awe, penultimate draft (1 of 2), 2004 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - The Days of Awe, penultimate draft (2 of 2), 2004 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - The Days of Awe, draft (1 of 2), circa 2005 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - The Days of Awe, draft (2 of 2), circa 2005 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - The Days of Awe, reviews, 2005 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - The Days of Awe, cover, 2005 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - The Days of Awe, reviews, 2005 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - The Days of Awe, marketing, 2005 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - The Days of Awe, cover proof, 2005 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - The Days of Awe, notes, 2000s (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - The Days of Awe, research, 2003 (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - The Days of Awe, research, 2000s (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - The Days of Awe, notebook, 2006 (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - The Pilgrim, "Carpentry", 2006 (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - The Pilgrim, "Calender 1618", 2006 (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - The Pilgrim, "Aboard Ship", 2006 (Box 13, Folder 17)
  - The Pilgrim, "Ship", 2006 (Box 13, Folder 18)
  - The Pilgrim, "Emmanuel Maps", 2006 (Box 13, Folder 19)
  - The Pilgrim, "Mad Mary, Mark", 2006 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - The Pilgrim, "The Pilgrim - General", 2006 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - The Pilgrim, proposal for book, 2006 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - The Pilgrim, "Dorchester, Wellcome, Cambridge", 2006 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - The Pilgrim, "Map and Info Charring Cross", 2007 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - The Pilgrim, "Sheep", 2007 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - The Pilgrim, "The Book of Scots", 2007 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - The Pilgrim, "Felon", 2007 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - The Pilgrim, "Sarah's Death", 2007 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - The Pilgrim, "Map of London", 2007 (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - The Pilgrim, "Ship, Betrothal...", 2007 (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - The Pilgrim, "Chapter 3", 2007 (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - The Pilgrim, "Terry's Letters", 2007 (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - The Pilgrim, "London Fair", 2007 (Box 14, Folder 14)
  - The Pilgrim, "Emmanuel (Cambridge)", 2007 (Box 14, Folder 15)
  - The Pilgrim, "Cost of Staffing Houses", 2007 (Box 14, Folder 16)
  - The Pilgrim, "Superstition", 2000s (Box 14, Folder 17)
  - The Pilgrim, "Appletree", 2000s (Box 14, Folder 18)
  - The Pilgrim, "When Sarah Dies", 2000s (Box 14, Folder 19)
  - The Pilgrim, "Last Letter", 2000s (Box 14, Folder 20)
  - The Pilgrim, reading of excerpts, 2000s (Box 14, Folder 21)
  - The Pilgrim, notes, 2000s (Box 14, Folder 22)
  - The Pilgrim, "Father - (last words)", 2000s (Box 14, Folder 23)
  - The Pilgrim, "Letter From Roger to Charles", 2000s (Box 14, Folder 24)
  - The Pilgrim, "Last Sentence", 2000s (Box 14, Folder 25)
  - The Pilgrim, "Mad Woman Maypole", 2000s (Box 14, Folder 26)
  - The Pilgrim, "Robin Barstow", 2000s (Box 14, Folder 27)
  - The Pilgrim, themes, 2000s (Box 14, Folder 28)
  - The Pilgrim, "Dorset", 2000s (Box 14, Folder 29)
  - The Pilgrim, "Looking Glass", 2000s (Box 14, Folder 30)
  - The Pilgrim, "Conversations", 2000s (Box 14, Folder 31)
  - The Pilgrim, "Suicide", 2000s (Box 14, Folder 32)
  - The Pilgrim, "After Return to Farm", 2000s (Box 14, Folder 33)
  - The Pilgrim, "Sheep", 2000s (Box 14, Folder 34)
  - The Pilgrim, "Beginning of Charles Regeneration", 2000s (Box 14, Folder 35)
  - The Pilgrim, "Retired Physician of Melancholy", 2000s (Box 14, Folder 36)
  - The Pilgrim, "Patch's Suicide to Sheep Shearing", 2000s (Box 14, Folder 37)
  - The Pilgrim, "Plot from Charle's 1st Stay on Farm", 2000s (Box 14, Folder 38)
  - The Pilgrim, "Poem", 2000s (Box 14, Folder 39)
  - The Pilgrim, Grammar School, 2000s (Box 14, Folder 40)
  - The Pilgrim, "Charles - Melancholy", 2000s (Box 14, Folder 41)
  - The Pilgrim, "Church", 2000s (Box 14, Folder 42)
  - The Pilgrim, "Uncle's Letter", 2000s (Box 14, Folder 43)
  - The Pilgrim, "Faustus Quote", 2000s (Box 14, Folder 44)
  - The Pilgrim, "Father Z - Redemption", 2000s (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - The Pilgrim, notes, 2000s (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - The Pilgrim, "London", 2000s (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - The Pilgrim, "Phrases", 2000s (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - The Pilgrim, research, undated (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - The Pilgrim, notebook, 2007 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - In the Reign of Peace, drafts, undated (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - In the Reign of Peace, manuscripts, undated (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - In the Valley, manuscript, undated (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Making Good, clipping, undated (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Making Good, manuscript, undated (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Making Good, draft, undated (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - A Pile of Stones, manuscript, undated (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - A Pile of Stones, pressing plate, undated (Box 56, Folder 5)
  - The Prisoner, drafts, undated (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - The Prisoner, copies, undated (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Via Yavnch, notes, undated (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - Via Yavnch, draft, undated (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - Via Yavnch, manuscript, undated (Box 16, Folder 13)
  - Via Yavneh, medical report, 1970 (Box 57, Folder 9)
  - The Rise and Fall of Adolph Hitler, screenplay, undated (Box 16, Folder 14)
- Personal Papers, 1942-2012; Series 3
  The Personal Papers series contains materials not directly related to Nissenon's professional writing, including his personal journal entries, papers related to his family, and correspondence. Of particular note is the "journal" sub-series which provides an excellent narrative of Nissenson's life from his own perspective. This series spans Nissenon's entire life from the 1940s to the 2010s.
  - Audiovisual and photographs, 1955-2003, undated; Subseries 3.1
    - Photographs, 1962-2003 (Box 55, Folder 4)
    - Photographs, 1955-2001 (Box 55, Folder 5)
    - "Jimmy Nissenson", undated (Box 56, Folder 6)
      Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
      Audiocassette; approximate run time: unknown
  - Clippings and maps, 1960s-2010s; Subseries 3.2
    - Clippings, 2010s (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - Clippings, 2000s (Box 21, Folder 2)
    - Clippings, 1990s (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - Clippings, 1980s (Box 58, Folder 4)
    - Clippings, 1980s (Box 20, Folder 18)
    - Clippings, 1970s (Box 20, Folder 16-17)
    - Clippings, 1960s (Box 20, Folder 15)
    - Maps, 2001 (Box 54, Folder 5)
    - Maps, 1970 (Box 54, Folder 4)
    - Maps, 1967 (Box 54, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1950s-2010s; Subseries 3.3
    This sub-series contains all of Nissenson's written correspondence from the 1960s to the 2010s. In the 2000s and 2010s this includes emails, which were printed out. All correspondence with Cynthia Ozick was set aside in Box 21, folder 4.
    - With Cynthia Ozick, 1960s - 2000s (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 1980s (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1980s (Box 25, Folder 2)